{
  "reference_number": "3113",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should not be buying (probably dodgy) emissions credits from other countries, or sell any surplus of ours to other countries. If the\n world is going to achieve this, not just play market gambling games, we all need to pull our own weight with serious policy to achieve\n\n serious reductions asap."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Only if we meet our targets early and can reduce emissions even further. But that's unlikely on our present record!"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "If we do better than the target on one budget, the next budget should be for the same amount of reduction so we reach the overall\n goal faster. You know we have to tie our govts into this legislative programme"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "This is the exceptonal circumstance - the planet is frying."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I like the three government objectives for climate change policy: sustainable economy, global and local leadership and creating a just\n\n and inclusive society. I like the Treaty of Waitangi consideration. Bullet points 3-6, esp the 'in particular' bits, sound like a future\n Commission/govt could use them for good or ill - and they must be used to achieve the emissions reduction goals. I'd like to change\n the words 'in particular' for 'despite'. They must have some flexibility, sure, should look at these bullet point in order to achieve but\n\n may not use them to under-budget or under target or under achieve they have to get us to net zero by 2050 Can you please write it\nthat way? You know that before 2050 we risk getting another govt that doesn't give a damn. Could allow flexibility to maybe identify\n\nand include further factor themselves if necessary without needing new legislation"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "yes, well ahead of time."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the govt's energy and transport goals so far and the billion trees (only 217 each over 10 years), what worries me is that\n\nland use change policies won't be strong enough, it'll just be 'nudging' that gets nowhere, party political compromises etc. We need\nto seriously reduce dairy and other ruminants and move to more crops (instead of importing grains/pulses) and more horticulture and\n\nstop importing so much stuff we could grow, with freight emissions we don't count. Govt needs to MAKE this happen, not just\nencourage."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1-4 functions agreed. Not 5, that's buying other people's dodgy carbon credits again, isn't it? We MUST NOT allow that, we have to do\n\nour own reductions, meetin our own targets in this country."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "AND advises govt on stuff. Transparent monitoring and analysis of the ETS and how it's working and published advice to govt. Sorry,\ndon't trust every possible govt between now and 2050"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The 8 essential area of expertise should be pretty much covered between them, but they should also be able to second any\nexpertise they need. Never mind the business competitiveness, that's not the goal, we don't need BNZ on this. Not everybody needs\n\nto be a fancy professional, just expert and good at what they do and seriously personally concerned about climate change. Make\nsure there are lots of women and Maori and someone from our low lying Pacific territories all thinking about the future for our kids, not\n\nabout business as usual."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "No, that's a different issue, heavily involves local govt decision making, it's a whole other important project, might need a whole other\n\nCommission/body to work with this one. But at the moment I want us to focus on STOPPING change, not adapting to it!"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I like bullet points on top of p.48 and CC Adaption Tech Working Group and national adaptation plan, but this should not be conflated\ninto the work of the CC Commission in reducing our emissions, overviewing the ETS (since govt has chosen that as main plank) and\n\nhelping NZ prevent climate change. As in 14 above, this needs a whole different group and progamme of work involving local govt\nand different players. PS I hate the word resilient - it means 'oh how good you are at continuing to put up with shit' - and 'adaption' is a\n\nbad idea too, I don't want us to adapt because I don't think we can. How about 'Facing climate change'?"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes govt should be responsible for this, they'll probably have to pay out for various disasters, but as well as govt and buildiing it into\n\ngovt depts' role/programmes, there needs to be an overview body that reviews coordiinates directs reports, advises govt and local\ngovt, etc But not the CC Commission because this has a very different role/goal, they could work together where appropriate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Thank god government is finally taking this seriously, because it's seriously scary."
    }
  ]
}
